<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Advice to parents and children the sum of a few sermons contracted and published at the request of many pious hearers / by Daniel Burgess ...</title>
            <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30267</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5692A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4891</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12085556</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12085556</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53731</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30267)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53731)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 57:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Advice to parents and children the sum of a few sermons contracted and published at the request of many pious hearers / by Daniel Burgess ...</title>
                  <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 70, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. for Tho. Parkhurst ... and J. Lawrance ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements on [3] p. at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Child rearing --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53731:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53731:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ADVICE TO PARENTS and CHILDREN. The Sum of a few SERMONS, Contracted, and Publiſhed at the requeſt of many Pious Hearers.</p>
            <p>By <hi>DANIEL B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGESS,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>He ſhall turn the Heart of the Fathers unto the Children, and the Heart of the Children unto the Fathers, lest I come and ſmite the Earth with a curſe, <bibl>
                  <hi>Mal. iv. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide;</hi> and <hi>J. Lawrance</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:53731:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53731:2"/>
            <head>To the Flock Committed to my Care. Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe whoſe Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity Extorted this Publication.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu would not Excuſe, you muſt therefore Accept this ſmall Labour. Were it not for the Writing, I would not Name it a Labour. The Meditation and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of it were very Pleaſure to me. He knows it, who knoweth
<pb facs="tcp:53731:3"/>what my Heart feels in my Hopes of Benefiting you; and in my Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcernments thereof.</p>
            <p>I have contracted it; and the rather, becauſe my late <hi>Sermon</hi> of Early Converſion is gotten into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your Hands I preſume.</p>
            <p>Under the Law, he that built a new Houſe was to make a Battle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Roof of it; leſt any walking on the Roof, ſhould through their Imprudence fall from it. <hi>Deut. 22.8.</hi> God was not ſatisfied, to have Houſeholders only forbear Puſhing Men down. But Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to make Proviſion againſt their own falling down. So that no Man ſhould eaſily come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hurt in their Families. None ſhould ſlip, if he would not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="tcp:53731:3"/>leap down headlong, over the Battlements. Believe it, my dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Friends, the Law is ſtill in force. God is not content that your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be not by you put upon ſinful courſes. He Commands that they be by you kept from them. That you ſet up ſuch Spiritual Battle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in your Houſes, as ſhall make it hard for a Child to fall into them. I have directed you how to make thoſe Battlements. If you ſet them up, and your children will leap over them into Hell, yet your own Souls are delivered. If you do not ſet them up, their Blood will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at your Hands. To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their Perdition and your Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row thence, I have prepared for them, that which I muſt truſt you to deliver unto them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53731:4"/>
            <p>My Life is ſpent in Prayers and Pains for you and them. I hope, I do not Live a day, wherein I have not the help of your Holy Prayers. You do by this time know my need, and my deſire alſo.</p>
            <p>May every of you be Bleſſed in your children, and your children in you. May all the Graces of the Bleſſed Spirit, all the Promiſes of the Goſpel-Covenant, and all the Joys of the Heavenly Manſions, be the Lot of your Inheritance, and of theirs. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very Affectionate PASTOR, <hi>DAN. BURGESS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53731:4"/>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>An Introduction into the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe intended; <hi>ſc.</hi> In ſix memorable Poſitions concerning ſecond Table Duties: <hi>Or,</hi> Duties toward Man.</head>
               <p>THey are not few, whoſe high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Aim</hi> and <hi>Buſineſs</hi> is to cultivate <hi>Moral Vertues.</hi> Speaking but ſeldom and but little of the Holy Ghoſts <hi>ſupernatural Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> and <hi>Goſpel Graces.</hi> But, as its every where ſeen, they are the death of Morality where they come. And by ſetting it up in oppoſition unto <hi>Evangelical Obedience,</hi> they do, (eventually, however undeſigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53731:5"/>depoſe both of them. They that deſire <hi>no more,</hi> do not poſſeſs <hi>ſo much</hi> as true Morality. They that aſpire not to be <hi>Godly,</hi> do reach but unto counterfeit <hi>Honeſty.</hi> Men wiſe unto Salvation do know the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, between <hi>true Pearls</hi> produced by the beams of the <hi>Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs;</hi> and the <hi>falſe ones,</hi> that are formed by the ſmoaky heat of <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But they are alſo too many, who ſin on the contrary hand: Who, it may be do <hi>affect,</hi> and certainly do <hi>account</hi> themſelves to be very <hi>Saints,</hi> not being ſo much as <hi>Men.</hi> Yea, and wanting nothing more of <hi>Bruits</hi> then their <hi>Innocence.</hi> Neglecting Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties toward Man, as though they had never been required by God. Or, as though, being of the <hi>lower Hemiſphere,</hi> they were unworthy of their Thoughts and Care. But who has bewitched the one and the other? that they ſhould not diſcern the monſtrouſneſs of <hi>unregenerate Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53731:5"/>and of <hi>immoral,</hi> yea <hi>unnatural Piety.</hi> Of the two, it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, this latter is the moſt viſible monſter. Moraliſts, void of Gods Holy Spirit, are poyſonous <hi>Snakes,</hi> but with <hi>fairly painted Skins</hi> on their backs. Whereas Saints in Profeſſion, not having natural Affection and reaſonable Converſation, are <hi>Naked without any fig-leaf.</hi> Are Devils in black, without their <hi>cloven foot</hi> hid. Sepulchres, not <hi>painted,</hi> nor ſo much as <hi>covered.</hi> In a word; the Plant called <hi>the ſenſitive</hi> one, hath no more ſenſe then the loweſt Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but has a little faint reſemblance of it! Graceleſs men of the moſt refined Morals, are as truly dead in ſin as the moſt lewd men are; but they have a ſhadow of gracious Life. And that ſhadow it ſelf, is more then is attainable by your utmoſt Faſting and Prayer unto God, while you lead a courſe of Injuſtice and Uncharitableneſs unto Men.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:53731:6"/>
               <p>To prepare you for the Duties I am to commend, I premiſe theſe ſix Memorandums. I would have their Fire heat your Iron before I ſtrike.</p>
               <p>Poſ. 1. <hi>Duty unto Man, is required juſt ſo as Duty unto God himſelf is.</hi> I mean, as immediate duty unto God is required. The ſame God <hi>made</hi> the Law for both: And alſo <hi>wrote</hi> with his own hand the Law for that and for this. And cauſed the Law for both to be alike <hi>preſerved</hi> in the Ark. Nor are the three <hi>Motives</hi> prefixed in the Praeface unto the Law, reſtrictly put to urge us unto the obſervance of the Commands of the firſt Table only. No, but to engage our performance of thoſe of the ſecond Table alſo, the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares; (1.) He is Jehovah, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be Obeyed. (2.) He is the God of his Peoples Choice and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and therefore to be Obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. (3.) He is their Redeemer and Diſembondager, and therefore to be Obeyed.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:53731:6"/>
               <p>Poſ. 2. <hi>Duty unto Man, is in like ſort explicated in the word as Duty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God immediately is. The four ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Precepts</hi> of Duty unto God, are notably explicated in numberleſs Texts of Scripture. And ſo are the <hi>ſix Precepts</hi> of Duty unto Man. I will inſtance but in four, noted to my hand by Mr. <hi>Durham</hi> on the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue, <hi>p.</hi> 311, 312. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.39. We are bid <hi>to Love our Neighbours as our ſelves.</hi> Which teaches that our Duty unto Men, ought to be diſcharged with <hi>warmth</hi> of Affection. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. We are told <hi>we ſhould do unto all men, as we</hi> (regularly) <hi>would that men ſhould do unto us.</hi> Which inſtructs us unto <hi>impartiality</hi> and <hi>extent</hi> of affection. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.4. We are charged, <hi>not to look</hi> (ſingly) <hi>at our own intereſts, but at others.</hi> Which gives us to underſtand, that our Duty unto Men ſtands not only in Affection and good Wiſhes. No, but Conſideration and Action too are required. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:53731:7"/>12.10. <hi>Be kindly affectioned one to another with Brotherly Love, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour preferring one another.</hi> Which extraordinary words ſignifie to us, that our Duty unto Man is to be paid with naturally free inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</note> and very inward eſteem of him.</p>
               <p>Poſ. 3. <hi>Duty unto Man, is a fruit of Duty unto God.</hi> Of Flattery and Pageantry, I do not ſpeak; but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Duty, and ſuch Duty unto Man, as is acceptable unto God. This, all of it, grows from Duty unto God, as its root. Our Duty unto God, is double: Firſt, <hi>Submiſſion unto his Authority;</hi> Secondly, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion Practical of that Submiſſion.</hi> Now, till we ſubmit to his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and own him to be what he is unto us; we cannot be rightly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected unto our ſelves or unto any other Creature. And till we ſet our ſelves to expreſs our ſubmiſſion to his Power, by obſervance of his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53731:7"/>Precepts, we cannot ſquare aright one action toward them or our ſelves. But when we ſubject our ſelves to the divine <hi>Power,</hi> and conform our ways to the divine <hi>Precepts,</hi> what followeth? Why then, our Lunacy is over. Owning him our Head, we own every fellow Member too. And being by him governed, every juſt office to him and to our fellow Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is introduced. His Authority is ſufficient to oblige unto both; and his Laws are extant, obliging unto them, Wherefore, <hi>rendering unto God the things that are Gods, we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily render unto Man the things that are Mans.</hi> Whereas, while we are Rebels unto God we are Divels to our ſelves, and unto one another. And muſt needs be ſo; being that ſo long as we are in the ſtate of Rebellion, we are deſerted by the Spirit of all good; and are act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the clean contrary Spirit. Blind they are therefore, that ſee not the Nobility of ſecond Table duty in its
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53731:8"/>Heavenly Deſcent. It cometh from firſt Table-Duty; and therefore muſt needs partake of its Dignity and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence. It is very obſervable, that, according to what is ſaid, all ſecond Table-Duties are preſſed from the conſideration of the firſt. As thoſe of <hi>Subjects unto the Higher Powers,</hi> Rom. 13.1. <hi>Let every Soul be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Higher Powers. For there is no power but of God: the powers that be, are ordained of God. Of Wives</hi> to <hi>Husbands,</hi> Eph. 5, 22. <hi>Wives, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves unto your own Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, as unto the Lord.</hi> Of <hi>Children</hi> to <hi>Parents,</hi> Eph. 6, 1. <hi>Children, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey your Parents in the Lord: for this is right.</hi> Of <hi>People</hi> unto their <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> 1 Theſs. 5, 12. <hi>And we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, Brethren, to know them which Labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you.</hi> Of <hi>Servants</hi> to <hi>Maſters,</hi> Coloſ. 3, 22. <hi>Servants, obey in all things your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters according to the fleſh; not with eye-ſervice, as men-pleaſers, but in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53731:8"/>ſingleneſs of heart, fearing God.</hi> The one Agument unto all, is Conſcience of the firſt Commandment. Which, as the Great <hi>Luther</hi> well ſaid, <hi>Is in every Commandment to be understood,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Poſ. 4. <hi>Duty unto Man, is a very great Mean of Duty unto God.</hi> I have read of a Tree growing in a hot and dry Countrey, whoſe Leaves do drop a Liquor that excellently moiſtens and maintains the Root. Duty to God, is indeed the Root of Duty to Man: But Duty to Man is that whoſe influences do greatly contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Life and Livelineſs of that Root. A Truth ſo bright, that it needs no proof, nor meets with any denial. <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.3. Reverence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Parents, ſeemeth called for as a mean of the Sanctification of Sabbaths. And 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.2. We are plainly bid to do our great Duty to Kings and all in Authority, yea and to all Men; for this very end, that we may lead quiet Lives in all Godlineſs and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty. In a word, it is the Holy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53731:9"/>Spirits pleaſure, ever to verify this memorable ſaying; <hi>All Graces and Duties be mutually Mother and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter unto each other.</hi> Love of God, and his Service, brings forth Love and Serviceableneſs unto Man. And Love and Serviceableneſs unto Man, brings a like Love and Service of God. <hi>He that would not Love and Serve Men for their own ſakes, ſhould do both for the ſake of the Love and Service of God.</hi> A Duke would Court the Friendſhip of a Begger, if that would half ſo much promote his Friendſhip with the King.</p>
               <p>Poſ. 5. <hi>Duty unto Man is the only convincing proof of ſincerity and Duty unto God.</hi> Duties toward God, are, for the moſt part Spiritual and Inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. When you are true therein, who but God and Conſcience can ſee your Truth? The Duties toward God, that are Bodily and Viſible, are now in the Goſpel-day, all, very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and cheap. Very Hypocrites do not begrudge them, and unfeigned
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53731:9"/>Friends of God can never be known by them. 'Tis otherwiſe as to Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties toward Men. They are naked and open to Mens Eyes. Their Light as the Sun, ſhineth before all Men. And <hi>few will question your Piety, if they ſee your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Honeſty.</hi> For this reaſon it ſeemeth, that in the day of Judgment Chriſt inſiſteth upon Chriſtians Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Second Table. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.35. Becauſe they are the moſt ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diſcoveries of Faith and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and fitteſt to juſtifie Saints be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World. The Servants of God, are obliged to ſhew abroad who their Maſter is. But they have no way to do it without that which is foreſaid. <hi>Therefore is it that the World ſo hardly believeth us Chriſt's Diſciples, becauſe we ſo little Love one another.</hi> They will acknowledge us his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, when they ſee more of his Livery, which is Love, among us.</p>
               <p>Poſ. 6. <hi>Duty to man hath Promiſes of Reward, as well as Duty unto God.</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:53731:10"/>Wonderful, yet moſt certain this is. The <hi>Fifth Command</hi> is known to be called the firſt <hi>with</hi> Promiſe. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.2. The <hi>Second,</hi> hath but a general Promiſe made to the Keepers of the whole Law: The Fifth hath a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Promiſe made to the Keepers of that ſingle Commandment. Let it never be doubted therefore, but that it ſhall be richly Rewarded by God, whatever at his Command you perform toward Man. Even toward the pooreſt Child. <hi>The Gift of a Cup of Water, ſhall be as truly rewarded as Martyrdom it ſelf.</hi> And be it known unto you Parents and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that of all Duties between Man and Man, the greateſt are thoſe between you. The Fifth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeemeth the Hinge of both Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. And, by its place, to ſpeak thus much. <hi>ſc. That in order to the Knowledge and Obedience of all the other Commandments, it is highly neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that the Fifth be well Known and Obeyed.</hi> It is true, Natural Parents are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53731:10"/>not all that be meant therein. All true Governors are included. But Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents only are mentioned, as being the <hi>first Governors</hi> we have; ſome years before Kings take notice of us. And as being the <hi>Principal Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors</hi> to whom we are moſt obliged, as the Authors of our Beings: and thoſe whoſe Government is not foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Choice and Contract, as others is, but in Nature it ſelf. Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſidered, I proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Parents Adviſed to their more Genearl and Particular Duties. And preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Motives thereto.</head>
               <p>The Duty of Parents to Children, is imply'd and concluded in the Fifth Commandment. It thus ſummarily expreſſed in the <hi>Weſtminſter Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies Larger Catechiſm. It is required of Superiors, according to that power they receive from God, and that relation wherein they ſtand, to love, pray for, and bleſs their Inferiors; to inſtruct,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53731:11"/>counſel, and admoniſh them; counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing, commending, and reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as do well; diſcountenancing, reproving, and chaſtiſing ſuch as do ill; protecting and providing for them all things neceſſary for ſoul, and body; and by grave, wiſe, holy, and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary carriage, to procure Glory to God, honour to themſelves, and ſo to preſerve that Authority which God hath put upon them.</hi> I will tranſcribe no more of our many Summaries. But propoſe theſe particulars which I take to be comprehenſive. And ſuch that God will judge all the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecters of; and not hold them guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, however full they be of excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>Knowing the Terror of the Lord,</hi> I thus inſtruct and perſwade every Chriſtian Parent,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Be Exemplary in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> Ill Example, is the rankeſt Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the World. Parents ill Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is the worſt that Children can have. I know not what God hath forbid or required, if he forbids not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53731:11"/>ill, and requires not good Example. Good Example, for Duty foreſaid. Wouldſt be a good Parent? Thou canſt not, till thou doſt underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, affectionately, and practically keep the Goſpel-Covenant. Owning the Engagement of thy Holy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, renewing it at the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, obſerving it in all thy ways to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, other Men, and thy ſelf. You that do not this, ye bid your Children not to do it: In practice, ye bid 'em. And ye who bid them, not to do this, ye bid them (virtual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) be Atheiſts and Devils and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, to God and to your ſelves. As little as ye think of it, this ye do. God, and Godly Men, count you ſo to do. Parents, Parents, con ye well <hi>Job</hi> 22, 21, 22, 23. <hi>Job</hi> is adviſed to <hi>Acquaint himſelf with God, to receive and lay up God's Word in his Heart, to return unto the Almighty:</hi> (that is, to do all I have here foreſaid:) And for his encouragement he is then told, his relative Duties will come on
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53731:12"/>with their Bleſſings. <hi>He ſhall be built up,</hi> that is, he ſhall have more Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. And <hi>he ſhall put away Iniquity far from his Tabernacles;</hi> that is, he ſhall be a good Father and Maſter, and remove the Iniquity of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants; and promote Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily-Godlineſs. Which, without that courſe preſcribed, he could not expect to do. <hi>Preceptive Teaching alone, is a little more than, a Cypher; 'tis practical Teaching is the Figure.</hi> The Language that God binds Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and all Teachers to uſe, is this. <q>Come with me, unto this and that Duty. Fly with me, from this and that Sin. Mourn with me, for this and that Omiſſion and Commiſſion ſinful. Delight with me, in this and that Holy Service.</q> And be it written on all our Walls, <hi>They that are not Patterns to their Children be plagues to their Children.</hi> They who give them not good Example, give them nothing good; at leaſt, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like to do them good. For a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53731:12"/>
                  <hi>grain</hi> of bad Example doth an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times more hurt, than a <hi>pound</hi> of good Counſel (ordinarily) doth good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Be as full of prayer, as St.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin's <hi>Mother.</hi> That Holy Creature got her Son and her Husband Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by her Prayer. But not by ſlight and ſleepy Prayer. Think of this, Parents! As their greateſt Wickedneſs makes not Prayer hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, ſo your greateſt Sanctity makes not Prayer uſeleſs. Our Redeemer, whoſe Obedience is Meritorious, he himſelf asks, before God gives. Nor will God give, till in his Name ye ask. Ordinarily, he will not. But if ye ask not amiſs, ye can never miſs of what ye ask. And I will be allowed to ſay; Prayer for our Children is that Duty to them, without which we can diſcharge none. We muſt be joyned to God in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, before we can right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pray. And we muſt Pray, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can expect to benefit our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53731:13"/>ſelves or our Children by any means poſſible. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.18, 20. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> prayed for <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and that warmly. And what ſays the Text? <hi>God ſaid, and as for</hi> Iſhmael <hi>I have heard thee, behold I have bleſſed him and will make him Fruitful, and will multiply him exceedingly: twelve Princes ſhall he beget, and I will make him a great Nation. David</hi> prayed hard for <hi>Solomon</hi> his Son. <hi>O Lord God of</hi> Abraham, Iſaac, <hi>and of</hi> Iſrael <hi>our Fathers, give to</hi> Solomon <hi>my Son a perfect heart to keep thy Commandments and thy Statutes</hi> 1 Chron. 22, 12, 1 Chron. 29, 18, 19. The <hi>ſeventy ſecond Pſalm is</hi> David's <hi>Prayer for his</hi> Solomon, Parents; Of all things be not niggardly of your prayers for your Children! Rather deny them Victuals and Drink. For many can give them both, that cannot put up prayers for them. And the ſame may be ſaid of the will as of the power of moſt. I know few do think it, but 'tis true, <hi>a ſtock of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53731:13"/>prayers is a richer Child portion, than a ſtock of broad Gold,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Be Catechizers through the whole compaſs of the words of Eternal Life.</hi> Suffer not thy Child to ſay, there is one Truth, or one Grace, or one Duty neceſſary to Salvation, that thou kneweſt but never taughteſt him. Who ever doubted, but if a Man had a blind Child, he was bound to uſe all the likely means he could come by, to recover it's ſight. I am very confident that <hi>Adam, Seth, Noah,</hi> and <hi>Sem,</hi> were, all, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſers. From the Cradle, the Church was ſtill kept up by Catechiſing. Of <hi>Abraham,</hi> God ſpeaks plainly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 19. <hi>For I know him, that he will command his Children and his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord, to do Juſtice and Judgment; that the Lord may bring upon</hi> Abraham <hi>that which he hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of him. David</hi> and <hi>Bathſheba</hi> too Catechiſed <hi>Solomon</hi> ſoundly. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.2, 3. <hi>I go the way of all the Earth:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53731:14"/>be thou ſtrong therefore, and ſhew thy ſelf a Man. And keep the charge of the Lord thy God, to walk in his ways, to keep his Statutes and his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and his Judgments and his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, as it is written in the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>that thou mayeſt proſper in all that thou doeſt, and whitherſoever thou turneſt thy ſelf.</hi> 1 Chron. 28.9. <hi>And thou,</hi> Solomon <hi>my Son, know thou the God of thy Father, and ſerve him with a perfect heart, and with a willing mind: for the Lord ſearcheth all hearts, and underſtandeth all the imaginations of the thoughts: if thou ſeek him, he will be found of thee; but if thou forſake him, he will cast thee off for ever.</hi> Prov. 31.1. <hi>The words of King</hi> Lemuel, <hi>the propheſie that his mother taught him. Lois</hi> and <hi>Eunice</hi> are praiſed on this account. 2 Tim. 1.5, 3, 15. <hi>When I call to remembrance the unfeigned Faith that is in thee, which dwelt firſt in thy Grand-mother</hi> Lois, <hi>and thy Mother</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice; <hi>and I am perſwaded that in thee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53731:14"/>alſo. And that from a Child thou haſt known the holy Scriptures, which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make thee wiſe unto Salvation, through Faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus. After the death of the Apostles, the Churches had Officers for the ſingle work of Catechiſing. Clemens, Origen, Cyril,</hi> ſucceſſively held that work at <hi>Alexandria.</hi> And truly Parents, you had need take it up your ſelves now. For you are your Childrens firſt <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> as well as their <hi>Guides</hi> and <hi>Rulers.</hi> And an uncatechiſing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent is a non-preaching Miniſter; which is ſo bad a Creature, that one hath ſaid, <hi>He thought Hell was pav'd with their Skuls.</hi> This forget not, I beſeech you; every prayer you make for your Children, that is not followed with your pains with them, is a very mocking of God and of them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Be as kind as ever you can with good Conſcience.</hi> Never provoke 'em, or by unneceſſary hard looks, words, or acts, diſcourage them. <hi>Col.</hi> 3, 21.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53731:15"/>
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4. God expreſly forbids you. But catch at every opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to encourage them to begin and go on to do well. This God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth you to do toward all, and eſpecially, your own Children, I trow. It was wickedly that <hi>Saul</hi> called his Son <hi>Jonathan,</hi> Son <hi>of the perverſe and wicked Woman;</hi> and more wickedly that he threw a Javelin at him: which cauſed him to riſe up in fierce anger, which was very contrary to the Reverence of a Parent. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.30, 33, 34. And as wicked were the <hi>blind man</hi>'s cow-hearted Parents, who ſhrunk from his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and left him to ſhift for himſelf, ſaying, <hi>he was of age,</hi> forſooth. <hi>Jo.</hi> 9.21. Praiſe worthily, <hi>Joaſh</hi> ſtood by his Son <hi>Gideon</hi> in the conteſt, <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.29, 30, 31, But in brief: the Holy Ghoſt ſuppoſeth good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to brook what may be born in their Children. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. <hi>As a Father ſpareth his Son.</hi> For Mothers, ſee <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.13. <hi>As one whom his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53731:15"/>mother comforteth.</hi> Convince your Children, if it be poſſible, that you <hi>love</hi> them as the apple of your eyes. And do <hi>pray</hi> and <hi>labour</hi> to make ſweet their Time and Eternity. Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them but as God doth, drawing them with the Cords of a Man, the Bonds of Love. Shewing them by the likeneſs of your Government, that 'tis in God's ſtead that you do Rule over them. Even the God who is Love. And whoſe <hi>ſeverity</hi> is as rare as Thunder, while his <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity</hi> is as common as the day Light. Flints will break upon Wool, that will not upon Iron. But,</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Abhor</hi> David<hi>'s kindneſs unto</hi> Adonijah. It is ſaid, <hi>That</hi> David <hi>had not diſpleaſed him at any time, in ſaying, why haſt thou done ſo?</hi> 1 Kings 1.6. This kindneſs is the bloodieſt Cruelty. God pronounceth ſuch Parents Haters of their Children. <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.24. <hi>He that ſpareth his rod, hateth his ſon;</hi> he carries it miſchievouſly towards his ſon, as tho'
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53731:16"/>he did hate him. <hi>David</hi> found it ſo, when <hi>Adonijah</hi> was in Rebellion. <hi>Iſaac</hi> found it ſo, when his ſon <hi>Eſau,</hi> whom he had ſuffered to ſport out his time in Hunting, came to grieve his heart and his Wives. <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.27. <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.35. <hi>Eli</hi> found it ſo, when, for the indulged ſins of his coldly rebuked Children, he was ſentenced terribly by God, and his whole Family alſo. His <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phineahs</hi> being both doom'd to die in a day. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. Government, is a high Talent; Dominion maketh like unto God. Fooliſh fondneſs proſtitutes unto contempt. And ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to ſcorn any Governor, yea the God for whom he Governeth. A wickedneſs, that, I think, God never lets go unrevenged in this World it ſelf. A wickedneſs, that many at the Gallowes have ſaid, was the cauſe of their periſhing thereon. A wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, that ſlays more of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the <hi>Nobility, Gentry</hi> and <hi>Commonalty,</hi> than any other appears
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53731:16"/>to do. Parents, as you value your Childrens Souls, be ſure to abhor <hi>Tyranny</hi> on one hand, and <hi>Anarchy</hi> on the other. Be not ſo Cruel as to give them their wills in no thing, or to deny them their wills in any thing that is good. Nor ſo much more Cruel, as to give them their wills in every thing, or in any one ſinful thing. <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.15. <hi>The Rod and Reproof give Wiſdom, but a Child left to himſelf bringeth his Mother to ſhame.</hi> Apes be not the only Bruits that hug their Whelps to death. Be it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred that I ſay: <hi>Bruitiſh is that Parent that ever corrects a Child but when 'tis neceſſary, or ever doth it not to the ſubduing of his Spirit when it is neceſſary.</hi> When it comes unto a conteſt, he that lets his Child out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brave him, doth ſhame himſelf, and (in a ſenſe) murder and damn his Child. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.13, 14. <hi>If thou beateſt him with the rod he ſhall not dye. Thou ſhalt beat him with the rod, and ſhalt deliver his ſoul from Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:53731:17"/>6. <hi>Lay out, and lay up for your Children.</hi> They have Bodies as well as Souls. God commits to you the care of both. And requires that, next to their Souls, you be of all things moſt kind to their Bodies. That you lay out upon them what is meet; for <hi>Comfort,</hi> and <hi>Ornament,</hi> as well as <hi>Neceſſity:</hi> Though ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring <hi>ſuperfluity;</hi> into which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream moſt Parents do run. It is an odious ſight, when Children are Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled, Fed, and Lodged very <hi>poorly,</hi> though the Parents are all <hi>richly.</hi> It ſhews that the Parents are Monſters, and it tempts the Children to be Vipers. <hi>He that is greedy of gain, in this way as well as others, troubleth his houſe, Prov.</hi> 15.27. This unnatural vicious niggardice unto Children, makes a Waſps neſt of a Family. Laudable was <hi>Jeſſe</hi>'s liberal care for his Sons: 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.17. <hi>Jeſſe ſaid unto David his Son, take now for thy Brethren an Epha of this parched Corn, and theſe ten Loaves,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53731:17"/>and run to the Camp to thy Brethren.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An Epha contained about ten Pottles, a ſufficient allowance for a days food.</note> 
                  <hi>And carry theſe ten Chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to their Captain, and look how thy Brethren fare, and take their pledge. Jacobs</hi> care for his Sons was alike lovely; <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.14. <hi>He ſaid to Joſeph, Go I pray thee, ſee whether it be well with thy Brethren. and well with their Flocks, and bring me word again.</hi> But whatever you lay out upon your Children, you are obliged alſo to lay up for them. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Prodigals, that ſpend all their income, (unneceſſarily, I mean;) are horrid Felons.</hi> And rob their Children of their due. Parents ought to exerciſe together great <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,</hi> and great <hi>Frugality,</hi> with an eye to their Childrens needs. Their needs of charge to the ſetting of them in proper and <hi>comfortable Callings;</hi> and afterward to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of them in <hi>convenient Matches.</hi> In which a wiſe Man would take the moſt curious care, next to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53731:18"/>Salvation of his Childs Soul. But it need not be ſaid, how little the greateſt care uſeth to do in either their Callings or Matches, without a provided ſtock of <hi>that which anſwers all things. Jacobs</hi> queſtion is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every faithful Parents: <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.30. <hi>And now when ſhall I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for my own houſe?</hi> They Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly conſider, <hi>if they provide not for them, they are worſe than Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. Parents, lay to heart what I tell you: If our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be <hi>without Callings,</hi> they be outlaws from Gods Kingdom. If they be in <hi>bad ones,</hi> they are in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Temptations. If we lay not up what we (innocently) can for them, they are not like to have good ones. If through our <hi>Sloth, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality,</hi> or <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> they do miſs of good ones, what an action have they againſt us? It would cut the heart of a gracious Parent to have his Children ſay, as <hi>Labans</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.14, 15. <hi>Is there
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53731:18"/>yet any portion for us in our Fathers houſe? Are we not counted of him ſtrangers? And hath he not quite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured alſo our money.</hi> Neither are your Children, Angels. It is your duty to provide, ſeaſonably, for their diſpoſal in Marriage. Some delay it, looking after a Match more rich then yet offers: Others delay, as loth to part with ſo much of their Riches as is requiſite. But commonly you pay dear for your delays. <hi>Lot</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed to diſpoſe of his Daughters, and he deeply ſuffered for it. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.30, 31, 32. <hi>Judah</hi> delayed; ſuffered for it, and confeſſed it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.26. <hi>Tamar</hi> (that played the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot) <hi>hath been more righteous then I, becauſe that I gave her not to Shelah my Son.</hi> Unto this delay of Parents muſt be aſcribed, the invincible <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly,</hi> the <hi>Distraction,</hi> the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery,</hi> the <hi>temporal Ruin</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy</hi> of thouſands of Engliſh Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Hiſtory tells us of many that have conſpired and got their Parents
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53731:19"/>murdered, for croſſing them in their Matches. I would that Religious Parents could but look into the hearts of all the Children that they croſs herein, and ſee the reſentments of them. But I add this word only more; <hi>Forbidding to marry is a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Divels, among Papiſts; and ſeems to be a practice of Divels among many Proteſtants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I proceed unto ſome more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Counſels. Calculated for the greateſt number of Parents, who do need them. Thoſe, more rare ones, that do not, may overlook them. I exhort thoſe who are <hi>weak enough</hi> to want, and <hi>humble enough</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept theſe Lines, as followeth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand and lament your Childrens ſin and miſery.</hi> Know and conſider what their natural unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed ſtate is. Till you do ſo, you will neither incline nor underſtand how to do your Duties. For you are without your Motive and your Rule. I often think and ſay; <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53731:19"/>ſin muſt be more learned, before Parents duties be better practiced.</hi> Did you know your Children to be ſick, and know their diſeaſe too; I do perſwade my ſelf you would not ſo generally neglect their cure.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Begin their Education very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> The Twig greeneſt, bends eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. They that tame Lions, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert very many Sinners, break them when they are very young. <hi>Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſs of will, ruines the World:</hi> But young Stomachs are moſt eaſie to be pulled down. Beſides, God is honoured by your <hi>hast</hi> to make your Child honour him. And moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly he honoureth and bleſſeth that haſt. The ſooner you are do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the more and better you are like to do.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Employ them conſtantly.</hi> Keep them out of Idleneſs, as you would out of the Fire, or out of the Thames. Hold them alwayes Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, Hearing, or Doing. <hi>Rather make them ſweep the Houſe, then ſtand
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53731:20"/>idle in it.</hi> Find ſome good work or innocent for all their time, if ye would have them do good in a good manner at any time. Neither Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, nor Men, can refrain from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, any longer then employed in good.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Keep them from bad Company.</hi> That is Pitch; and if we let them touch it, they muſt be defiled. Their Playfellows worſt words and wayes; get into the beſt of them, very ſoon. And your own, and their Maſters beſt words and blows will not ſo ſoon get them out. Who knows it not? <hi>Company is one of the moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful means of Grace, or the contrary.</hi> It opens the doors of the Soul, more then any, unto Good or unto Evil.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Make them neither too Bold with you, nor too Fearful of you.</hi> Not too <hi>Bold;</hi> they be not Equals. Nor too <hi>Fearful;</hi> they be not your meer Servants neither. Familiarity will bring them to contemn you, and your Government. Fear will make
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53731:20"/>them to hate both. Children be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Creatures, they love them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and love thoſe that love them. You muſt give them ſuch <hi>freedom</hi> with you, as may ſpeak your love of them. For the ſenſe of that, will make it a pain to them to diſpleaſe you; and a pleaſure to gratifie you. But you muſt not give them ſuch a <hi>Liberty,</hi> as doth directly carry them to Licentiouſneſs. For alas, poor things, if you will make them as bold as <hi>Equals,</hi> they (before ever they are aware of it,) will make themſelves as bold as <hi>Superiours.</hi> In a word: You muſt neither make them too <hi>timorous</hi> to look upon you, not too <hi>audacious</hi> to be awed by a look of yours. Let them love to ſee you, and fear to let you ſee ought but what you like in them.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Let the doctrine of God and of his Covenant word, be firſt, and moſt taught them.</hi> The ſixteen things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God which I have Printed for your uſe, may be leiſurely drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53731:21"/>into very young Minds. So may my ſhort account of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace. Till they are learnt, I know not what can be profitably learnt. And when they are, all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is more eaſily learnt. <hi>Early</hi> and <hi>frequently,</hi> and <hi>moſtly</hi> inculk upon them; How great and good God is, what a Covenant his Goſpel preſents, what an Engagement and Encouragement Holy Baptiſm is. <hi>Happy be the Scholars who are ſet to learn firſt things in the firſt place.</hi> Order gives Perſpicuity, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuity makes Affection and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Speak of holy things in their Preſence, with the greateſt reverence poſſible.</hi> Poor Creatures, their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of you is the higheſt they have. They take you for wiſer then all the World. They believe beſt and love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt what they ſee you take to be ſo. And they will ſhrewdly gueſs by your Speech and Carriage, what it is you take for beſt, and what for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53731:21"/>worſt. Now a ſight of your prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God and Covenant duty to him above all things; and a ſight of your hating and dreading ſin and Gods diſpleaſure more then Pain or Death; what doth it on them? Truly, more good for ought I know, then is done by all things elſe to be named. Yea, and their hearing you ſpeak of <hi>Holy</hi> things but as of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> and their ſmelling out your low eſteem of them, is the greateſt bane of them that can be invented. If any thing more ſtrengthens their Original Corruption, 'tis ſomewhat that I have not yet underſtood.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Shew them by Words and Deeds your Love of beſt Miniſters and People, and your loathing of trifling Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and vain People.</hi> By this will they be brought to love the one and loath the other, before they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them. And be forengaged to Hearken to the beſt, and to be Deaf to the worſt. A benefit very great! And one whoſe influence is often
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53731:22"/>ſeen to laſt throughout the Lives of Men and Women. As is alſo the power of the contrary. I mean; when the curſed example of Parents bringeth Children to mock at Gods Prophets and People; and to eſteem as the pleaſanteſt Company, ſuch as make a God of this World, and make but a jeaſt of Religion. And this before they know themſelves, who are the beſt and wiſeſt, and who the moſt miſerable people and fooliſh. Scarcely one of an hundred is ever reduced, from the fatal er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſo <hi>early</hi> ſwallowed and <hi>blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>Make their Recreations to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their name.</hi> I mean, to be ſuch only, as do indeed Recreate, and Whet, and Sharpen. Such as do make for Health of Body and for Chearfulneſs of Mind; and leave them more fit, and not leſs fit for Buſineſs, then they found them. One of our Holy <hi>Martyrs,</hi> repented his having played at Cheſs. Biſhop
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53731:22"/>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> betimes left the uſe of Cards, as finding them an enſnaring Game. All I ſay is this; <hi>Games that do not exerciſe the Body, and do much ſtretch the ſinews of the Mind, and do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſt great ſumms of Time, theſe do bear the Superſcription of Satan.</hi> For in them, Play becomes a very work. And the Gameſter doth as a Mower, who ſhould ſpend all the day in whetting his Sithe.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Obſerve carefully each Childs pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Temper.</hi> The difference is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great. And the need to know it is great. For how ſhall you elſe ſuit your dealings unto it? You muſt never expect to obtain your end by unſuited means. <hi>If you are very rough with ſome Children, you frighten them not unto their duties but out of their wits.</hi> Others, will ſcarcely learn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing unleſs they be taught like the men of <hi>Succoth,</hi> with briars and thorns. And only a middle way, with ſweetneſs and ſeverity immixed, will reach others. Beſides, as every
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53731:23"/>Man, ſo every Child has ſome one or other <hi>ſupream ſin;</hi> that ſupports all the reſt; and being depoſed, the reſt would ſoon be mortified. Now the Childs temper being found, this <hi>King-ſin</hi> of his would not be long to ſeek. And this being well watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and reſiſted, great would be the hopes of the Childs deſired Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>I conclude with a few Motives, or moving Conſiderations. Do but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them, and neglect what is foreſaid if ye dare?</p>
               <p>C. 1. <hi>Your Children are Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by Creation and Redemption; and committed to your Tuition.</hi> O think what you would do for the <hi>Kings Child,</hi> if you had one of his to educate.</p>
               <p>C. 2. <hi>Your Children are your ſelves.</hi> Very parts of your ſelves. And is it no ſhame for you that are <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to neglect or but ſlightly care for your ſelves.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:53731:23"/>
               <p>C. 3. <hi>You are Baptized, and have had your Children Baptized, and at their Baptiſm you engaged to do all this.</hi> In your Baptiſm you were bound to do all I have named. You ſaw your. Children in their Baptiſm, bound to obey the whole Goſpel. And you then Promiſed to do all you could to help them to do it. Is all this very nothing?</p>
               <p>C. 4. <hi>You have more Advantages to do all, then all the World beſide hath.</hi> You beſt love, and are beſt beloved by your Children. You are nigheſt to them. You have greateſt power over them.</p>
               <p>C. 5. <hi>Your Honour, Pleaſure and Profit, is most concerned in your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens good.</hi> More then other Mens is. More than your own is in ought beſide, except your own Souls Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p>C. 6. <hi>You are they that have done your Children most hurt.</hi> You pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated or derived <hi>Adams</hi> ſin to them; through you they received
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53731:24"/>the Infection: And by your own ſins, you make ſad work for them too. Who ſhould help to ſave them if not you?</p>
               <p>C. 7. <hi>You know too, (do you not,) that 'tis by ill Education, next to Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Corruption, that the World is made ſuch a Hell as 'tis.</hi> And will you nevertheleſs give your Children no better Education?</p>
               <p>Oh be not ſo unmerciful! You begat them not Beaſts; oh do not breed them as ſuch. Mercy, mercy, have mercy on the Souls that muſt be Bleſſed or Miſerable for ever. And whoſe Life or Death ſeems next to Gods own hand, in yours. Help, oh help poor Babes ſo weak. And do not ſtay, till your Help is nothing worth, or much leſs then now. <hi>To murder Souls and your own Childrens, is fitter work for Divels then for you.</hi> O lay not out Pounds for their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, for every Peny you lay out for their Souls. O Pray, O Labour, O Wait, till God ſay to each of you, <hi>I
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53731:24"/>will pour my Spirit upon thy Seed, and my Bleſſing upon thy Off-ſpring. They ſhall ſpring up as among the Graſs, as Willows by the water courſes. One ſhall ſay, I am the Lords; and another ſhall call himſelf by the name of Jacob; and another ſhall ſubſcribe with his hand unto the Lord, and ſirname him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by the name of Iſrael. Iſa.</hi> 44.3, 4, 5. Be it known to as many as will not thus do, they are notorious enemies of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>World,</hi> And of their rotting names their Children will be forced to ſpeak <hi>Lies,</hi> or <hi>Nothing,</hi> or <hi>Evil</hi> things. The <hi>Speeches, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> of many Heathens, (which I may not here repeat,) ſhall one day ſhame them. But I conclude with Prayer. <hi>O God turn the Hearts of Engliſh Fathers to the Children, and do not come and ſmite us with thy Curſe!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:53731:25"/>
               <head>Children exhorted to their Duties unto their Parents. General Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Particular. Motives to both.</head>
               <p>In <hi>Priſons</hi> and upon the Gallows, poor <hi>Miſcreants</hi> do often exclaim, that their ruin began in diſobedience unto Parents. Nor can it be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but <hi>Hell</hi> rings with the ſame complaint. Hear the words of your Life, dear Children! Read ye theſe Lines, as though they had been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the finger of God before your eyes. And you were called to by name in every Paragraph. As ſure as they are any words they are Gods word. And his word unto you; to all and every one of you. And his word <hi>deſigned</hi> and <hi>qualified</hi> to help you keep all his whole word. The fifth Command is a directory for keeping all, of both Tables.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Love your Parents most dearly.</hi> Honour imports Love. When Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53731:25"/>are bid to give <hi>Honour to Wives as weaker Veſſels,</hi> they are bid to be tenderly affectionate towards them. All do ſo conſtrue it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. And when you are bid to Honour your Parents, you are bid to Love them. And ſo Love them, as thoſe to whom you are moſt engaged next to God himſelf. You muſt love God, much more. If they put you upon any thing diſpleaſing to God, you muſt then ſhew, that in compariſon of God, you do hate them. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26. That for Gods ſake you can <hi>forget your Fathers Houſe,</hi> leave it and be glad to be out of it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.10. That in God's Cauſe, you have <hi>Levi</hi>'s courage; read it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.9. You muſt <hi>equally</hi> Love your Mothers and Fathers. Fathers are put firſt, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. Mothers are put firſt, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.2. <hi>Ye ſhall fear every Man his Mother and his Father.</hi> Both muſt be Loved beſt. The Mother, is the Fathers Inferior, ſome ways;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53731:26"/>but ſhe is his equal as to their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. She is a Parent as well as he; and much more painfully ſo. God commands that ſhe ſhould have the ſame Love as he. And <hi>the ſelf-ſame Reward is promiſed to the Love of Mothers as of Fathers, and all Duty towards them.</hi> You muſt Love your Parents conſtantly, ſincerely, and eminently. Your Father muſt not be deſpiſed when <hi>poor,</hi> nor your Mother when ſhe is <hi>old, Prov.</hi> 23.22. Nor either of them, when they rebuke you for ſin. <hi>Pro.</hi> 29. Your Love muſt be pure, and not mercenary for gain from them. As <hi>Abſolom</hi>'s was, for all his Flattery, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. And it muſt be eminent. 'Tis unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to Love a Father or Mother no more than we Love the moſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial of our Friends in the World. <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> give Parents the Preheminence.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Honour your Parents moſt high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Next unto God, moſt highly.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53731:26"/>In your Thoughts, Words, and Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, Honour them. Fear to think an ill thought of them. Their faults forget and cover, this is praiſewor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japheth,</hi> are Bleſſed, and <hi>Cain</hi>'s poſterity Curſed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.22. to 28. Let every Speech unto your Parents be expreſly Reverent. <hi>Rachel</hi>'s to <hi>Laban</hi> was ſo, <hi>Let not my Lord be diſpleaſed.</hi> Gen 31.35. 'Tis unnatural when it is not ſo. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. <hi>A Son honoureth his Father:</hi> that is, naturally Sons do. <hi>Break a bone as ſoon as omit to bow it to your Parents.</hi> Irreverent geſtures of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy are wicked, moſt ſcandalouſly. <hi>Solomon</hi> bowed to his Mother. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.19. <hi>Joſeph bowed himſelf with his Face to the Earth, unto his Father;</hi> Gen. 41.12. Where I ſee not this threefold Reverence in you to your Parents, I cannot think you other than ignorant deſpiſers of God and your Parents.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:53731:27"/>3. <hi>Obey your Parents moſt abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> I mean, <hi>in the Lord,</hi> as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks. Where God forbids not, do what they bid you, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they bid you: though it be againſt your own minds and wills. For this is God's moſt Wiſe and Holy Will. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Children obey your Parents in all things, for this is well-pleaſing unto the Lord.</hi> Where is the honour required in the <hi>Fifth Commandment</hi> without this? Read <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.8, 9. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.17. Children, <hi>Rebecca</hi> and <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel</hi> kept Sheep at their Parents com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. <hi>Gen.</hi> 29. <hi>Jeſus. Chriſt</hi> himſelf was ſubject to <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> in their mean employment. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.57. <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.15. How wonderoufly yielded <hi>Iſaac</hi> to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> ſee <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.9.10. And the <hi>Rechabites</hi> to their Father, <hi>Jer.</hi> 35.5, 6, 7, to <hi>v.</hi> 11. He that ſays, I will not do what my Parents would have me, he therein ſaith alſo, I will
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53731:27"/>not do what God would have me. Unleſs he can ſay, therefore do I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey my Parents becauſe I ſhould otherwiſe ſin againſt God. A good Childs heart ſpeaks thus: Whatever I can do without ſin, let my Parents command, and ſpare not.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Requite your Parents moſt Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly.</hi> 1. Tim. 5.4. <hi>Let them learn with Piety at home, to requite their Parents: for that is good and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble toward God.</hi> The Honour in the <hi>Fifth Commandment</hi> includes Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence; which is called Honour, <hi>Numb</hi> 22.37. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, had you Kingdoms to give your Parents, they would not pay your Debt unto them. You muſt all your lives long be paying of it; you will never have paid the ſum to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. Never come out of your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents debt. Therefore, always, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their needs and your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, you muſt be paying your Thank-Offerings. A Child is a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53731:28"/>
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. As thee <hi>his ſon that ſerveth him.</hi> Phil. 2.22. <hi>As a ſon with the Father hath he ſerved with me.</hi> You muſt ever promptly ſerve them to your power, in every inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent matter. And if they fall into want, you muſt ſupply them <hi>readily</hi> as ever they ſupplied you; and as <hi>liberally;</hi> and <hi>more richly</hi> too, if you are able. You muſt in many caſes, ſpare from your ſelves to give them. Yea you muſt lay out the leſs upon the Worſhip of God too, to beſtow on them. To withdraw from Parents, even for God's Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, was an abominable fault of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> condemned by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Mark</hi> 7.9, 10, 11, 12, 13. In a word; 'tis not enough if you do nothing to <hi>grieve</hi> your Parents. You ſin, if you omit any thing in the power of your hands to <hi>comfort</hi> them; and to make their Loyns bleſs you. Bleſſed are the <hi>Joſephs</hi> that nouriſh their Parents and Brethren! <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.12.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:53731:28"/>5. <hi>Behave your ſelves ſo, that you may be high Honours unto your Parents.</hi> I mean, ſo <hi>Holily</hi> toward God, ſo <hi>Righteouſly</hi> toward Men, ſo <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately</hi> toward your ſelves. So as may make for the Honour of your Parents. The Honour of their gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>prayers</hi> and their bleſſed <hi>pains</hi> took for you. So as may make both Town and Countrey have your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in more Notice and Reputation for you. This Counſel comprehends all. O what a World ſhould we have, if it were followed? Children come on and begin and ſet to mend this World. You cannot doubt but this my Counſel is certainly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the <hi>Fifth Commandment.</hi> You muſt needs know, he cannot Honour his Father and Mother, that is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and ſhame to them. Whoſe whole life caſts diſgrace on their <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Families,</hi> and <hi>Names.</hi> Yet ſo do theirs do, that obſerve not this Counſel. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.25. <hi>A Foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53731:29"/>ſon is a grief to his Father, and bitterneſs to her that bare him.</hi> Come, unleſs you will ſay plainly, ye will be Atheiſts; that your Converſion ſhall never make joy in Heaven; take this day my advice. Say juſt now, <q>If prayers and pains will prevail, I will make glad my Father and Mother that ever they had me given unto them. I will learn di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently every <hi>Truth</hi> they teach me, I will pray hard for every <hi>Grace</hi> they commend. I will perform ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly every <hi>Duty</hi> they ſet me. I will reſiſt every <hi>Lust</hi> and <hi>Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> they warn me of. I will imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate all the good I ſee in them. <hi>God,</hi> I will know. His <hi>Goſpel-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> I will enter, and live by. My <hi>Holy Baptiſm</hi> I will know and keep. The <hi>Lords Table</hi> I will prepare for and haſten to. <hi>Holineſs</hi> I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly perfect, in the fear of God. No Man living, ſhall ſay henceforth, that I wrong him wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53731:29"/>or do him right unwillingly. And neither of my Parents ſhall be able with truth to ſay, that I do ſo much as ſeem to forget my debt to them and its depth.</q> When this is truly ſaid, and with full purpoſe of heart, you then firſt begin to be good Children, and dutiful. Then you may be called, the <hi>Crown and Honour</hi> of your Fathers, as <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.6. and their very <hi>Glory,</hi> as it is <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9.11. Such as make them <hi>not aſhamed</hi> (but honoured) <hi>in the Gate,</hi> or in all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.4, 5. And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til you thus reſolve and declare, you are the clean contrary. For you are Fools. And <hi>he that begeteth a Fool, doth it to his ſorrow, the Father of a Fool hath no joy.</hi> 'Tis no joy, ſave to a Fool, to beget and breed up <hi>Slaves</hi> for the Devil and <hi>Fuel</hi> for Hell. And this Holy Parents do know, if you not, <hi>ſc.</hi> That "A wicked Child of Godly Parents is one of Earths ugly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt burthens; and (without won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53731:30"/>Grace intervening) one of Hells certaineſt Fire-brands.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>More particularly, I now Exhort You.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Be it for Conſcience ſake ſtill, that you Honour your Parents.</hi> Be ſure it be your deſire to pleaſe, and your fear to offend God, that makes you fear to offend and deſire to pleaſe your Parents. Read heedfully <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.3. <hi>Ye ſhall fear every Man his Mother and his Father and keep my Sabbaths.</hi> There's the Precept. <hi>I am the Lord your God;</hi> that is, you elſe offend me who am God, and your Covenant God. There is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. Charge your Conſciences to be your daily Remembrancers of this; that the true Honouring of Parents is a Fruit, whoſe Root is the true Honour of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Be it as you would receive and lay up Gold, that you receive and lay up the Advice your Parents give you.</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:53731:30"/>Have, and ſhew that you have as true a pleaſure in taking the one as the other from them. Convince their hearts that they do <hi>delight</hi> you, when they do <hi>inſtruct</hi> you. That would be an advantage to them and you too, beyond the expreſſion. Make them to ſee that what is impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto you, is not loſt. And that you treaſure up their ſayings, as the Sons of <hi>Caſſius</hi> did his Books. When it was threatned their Fathers Books ſhould be burnt; they anſwered, <hi>Then must you burn us too; for we have his Books in our hearts.</hi> Prov. 6.20, 21. My Son keep thy Fathers Commandment, and forſake not the Law of thy Mother. Bind them continually upon thy heart, and tye them about thy neck.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Convince your Parents that you much delight in their preſence.</hi> That you love to be near them, to hear their Wiſdom. Even little Children are <hi>tainted,</hi> when they like better to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53731:31"/>be in the Kitchen with the ſervants, than in the Parlor with their Parents. More grown ones be <hi>poyſoned,</hi> when they think themſelves then beſt, when fartheſt from holy Parents Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Counſel. Neither do love their perſons or their piety, if they love not their company. The <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal,</hi> when he had wandred from his Fathers Houſe, is ſaid to have been <hi>dead and loſt,</hi> Luke 15. Holy <hi>Joſeph</hi> bid his Brethren tell <hi>Jacob, Thus ſaith thy Son</hi> Joſeph, <hi>come down unto me, tarry not. Thou ſhalt be near unto me, thou and thy Children, and thy Childrens Children.</hi> Gen. 45.9, 10. And <hi>Ruth,</hi> (who loſt nothing by it) ſaid to her very Mother in Law, <hi>Intreat me not to leave thee, or to return from following after thee: for whither thou goest, I will go, and where thou lodgeſt I will lodge, where thou diest will I die.</hi> Ruth 1.16, 17. God ordered, that the advanced Captive ſhould, for a months time,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53731:31"/>bewail the loſs of her Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers converſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.13. But,</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Let all the houſe ſee, that your Parents Friends be yours, and your choiceſt ones.</hi> That your affection is ſwayed by theirs; and you cannot but love ſuch as they love. <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.10. <hi>Thy Fathers Friends forſake not.</hi> In loving my Parents, God and Men do ſhew me love; and my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents love of both, directs and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites me to the love of both, I am a Child unnatural, If I love not both the better for their loving and being beloved of my Parents. Hear <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> Exod. 15.2. <hi>The Lord is my ſtrength, he is my God,</hi> (my own) <hi>I will</hi> (therefore) <hi>prepare him an habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; my Fathers God, and</hi> (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) <hi>I will exalt him.</hi> Remember this, Children; and obſerve ye well; 'tis made an extreme aggravation of your ſin, that it is ſinned againſt the God of your Fathers. That is, againſt the God that was very kind to them,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53731:32"/>and was by them Honoured and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped. <hi>Judg.</hi> 2.12. <hi>They forſook the Lord God of their Fathers, and the anger of the Lord was hot againſt them.</hi> So <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.17. 'tis a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful charge, <hi>They Sacrificed unto Devils, to new Gods that came newly up, whom their Fathers feared not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Joy your Parents joys, and grieve their griefs,</hi> Let Sympathy ſhew your Unity. Let one joy of theirs, make you forget ſix troubles and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of your own. And one ſorrow of theirs, unſweeten as many comforts of your own. <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Sons and Daughters, <hi>all, roſe up to comfort him,</hi> 37.35. And <hi>Judah</hi> profeſſed he was not able to ſee his Father in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peradded trouble; <hi>How ſhall I go up to my Father, and the Lad be not with me? leſt peradventure I ſee the evil that ſhall come on my Father.</hi> Gen. 44.34. <hi>q. d.</hi> Rather had I be thrown in Irons my ſelf, and live and die in Slavery, than add to the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53731:32"/>of my Fathers gray hairs. So <hi>Reuben,</hi> before, when <hi>Joſeph</hi> was loſt; in the dread of his Father's ſore aking heart, bittterly cries out, <hi>The Child is not, and I, whither ſhall I go?</hi> Gen. 37.30. Hark alſo how <hi>Saul</hi> ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.5. <hi>Come let us return, leſt my Father take thought for us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Sleep not under your Parents diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure.</hi> If you any way raiſe it, uſe preſently all means to lay it. Be it a juſt or unjuſt Flame, ſhew you that 'tis one you are grievouſly tormented in. Eat not, Drink not, Buy and Sell not, till it be quenched. At leaſt till you have humbly offered all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible means for quenching it. I mean, all that you can do without offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, for pacifying them. <hi>Next to God's wrath, I would deprecate my Parents. And next unto his Bleſſing, I would deſire theirs. Numb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>If a Father ſpit in a Childs face, ſhould not the Child be
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53731:33"/>aſhamed ſeven days?</hi> Very <hi>Eſau</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, finding his Father's Bleſſing gone from him, could not bear it: but cried with tears, <hi>Bleſs me, even me alſo, O my Father. Gen.</hi> 27.13. And as for Heavenly <hi>Joſeph,</hi> when he heard his Father was ſick, he makes his utmoſt ſpeed to him, with his Sons alſo car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, that he might not miſs of his Bleſſing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Bear patiently, and bleſs God heartily for your Parents rebukes and corrections.</hi> Very often do the beſt Children need both. And it is of pure and greateſt kindneſs that good Parents do give both. Following them with holy prayers for Divine Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Go you therefore as oft as you are chaſtiſed, and ſay to this purpoſe: <q>O ſin, ſin, I hate thee. Had I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided thee, I had eſcaped this correction. My tender Parents puniſh themſelves in puniſhing me. Thou, O my ſin, haſt now trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled them and me. Much rather
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53731:33"/>had they have ſeen my Duties than heard my Out-cries. God bids them ſtrike, and not ſpare for my crying. Yea and tells them they hate me if they ſcourge me not.</q> 
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.18. <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.24. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren! of all Creatures they are moſt <hi>miſerable,</hi> that are <hi>incorrigible;</hi> and moſt <hi>incorrigible,</hi> that are <hi>impatient</hi> of reproof, and moſt <hi>impatient</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, that cannot bear it from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</hi> See <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Make your Parents in all things your Privy-counſellers.</hi> Acquaint them with your Secrets which are of any weight. Ask their advice in matters of any difficulty. This will ſpeak your eſteem of their Wiſdom, Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and Affection. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert all of them unto your uſe and benefit. O think of <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s words! <hi>Judg.</hi> 14.16. <hi>I have not told my Father nor my Mother, and ſhould I tell it thee?</hi> As if he had ſaid; <q>Of all Man-kind my Parents Breaſts be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53731:34"/>the Treaſuries of my thoughts. What I do not communicate unto them, I am not like to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to any Souls living.</q> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren! take your Parents advice, as to your <hi>Trades,</hi> your <hi>Matches,</hi> and all things of <hi>Moment,</hi> And as far as their words do agree with God's word, cloſely follow them. If ever you repent it, upon me be ſhame and your curſe.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Pray, and beg others prayers, for the converſion of your Parents if they be unregenerate. Abraham</hi> did all he could, to help his Father <hi>Terah</hi> out of his Idolatry. Compare <hi>Acts</hi> 7.3, 4. with <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. latter end and 12.1. and <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.2, 3. In this City I have the requeſt of ſeveral pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Children to pray for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Parents Converſion. And to ſend Letters and Books to ſome of them.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Praiſe and imitate all that is good in your living Parents, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:53731:34"/>honour them at their death.</hi> It is ſaid of the Vertuous Woman, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31, 28. <hi>Her Children riſe up, and call her Bleſſed.</hi> Every Godly Parent ſpeaks to his Children, in words much like the Apoſtles; <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.9. <hi>The things which you have both learned, and received, and heard, and ſeen in me, do; and the God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi> Happy the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that obey that charge! <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> Sons buried him honourably. <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.9. So alſo did <hi>Iſaacs</hi> Sons bury him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.29. As for <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob;</hi> it is ſaid, that <hi>Joſeph went up to bury his Father, and with him went up all the ſervants of Pharaoh, the elders of his houſe, and all the elders of the Land of Egypt. And all the houſe of Joſeph, and his Brethren, and his Fathers houſe: There went up with him both Chariots and Horſemen, and it was a very great company. Gen.</hi> 50.7, 8, 9. Some obſerve that <hi>Iſaac</hi> mourned the ſpace of three
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:53731:35"/>years for his Mother <hi>Sarahs</hi> death. He is then ſaid to have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted againſt his trouble, when he took <hi>Rebecca</hi> to Wife; <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.67. And they make it three years after the death of his Mother, that he Married. In a word; the Children that quickly forget Parents when they are Dead, did never overload them with honour when they were Alive. And 'tis a wonder if they themſelves do not both live undeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and dye unlamented.</p>
               <p>Now the Lord make the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Conſiderations to be indeed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives: And of good ſignificancy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to as many Children as ſhall read them.</p>
               <p>C. 1. <hi>Parents do moſt of all repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent God unto their Children.</hi> Their <hi>Generation</hi> ſhadows forth his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Their <hi>Education,</hi> his Propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, Government, and Love. To contemn Parents is to contemn God, in his moſt lively Repreſentatives unto Men.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:53731:35"/>
               <p>C. 2. <hi>Parents, are under God, the greateſt of Benefactors unto Children.</hi> By them God conveighs his Spiritual and Temporal Bleſſings unto Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.28. <hi>The Children are beloved for the Fathers ſakes. Prov.</hi> 20.7. <hi>The juſt man walketh in his integrity, his Children are bleſſed after him.</hi> Undutifulneſs to Parents, is the loweſt pit of ungratitude to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Mortals.</p>
               <p>C. 3. <hi>Parents, are next unto God, the principal Owners and Rulers of Children.</hi> God the ſole <hi>Proprietor</hi> hath made Children moſt eminently theirs. He gives his Servants Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for Rewards, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.3. God the ſupream and univerſal <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> hath made Parents his ſpecial Vicegerents. To Teach, Rule and Judge Children. Whoſoever there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reſiſteth Parents, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God; and is moſt aggravatedly Felon and Traitor.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:53731:36"/>
               <p>C. 4. <hi>Sins againſt Parents are most prolifical ſins.</hi> Such as do bear all ſort of ſins againſt God, Men, and our ſelves. If a Child honour not his Father and Mother whom he hath ſeen, how ſhall he honour God whom he hath not ſeen? If he Curſe his Father, and do not Bleſs his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that gave him his being; how ſhall he, as to others, Bleſs and Curſe not? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.7. <hi>In thee,</hi> (Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,) <hi>have they ſet light by Father and Mother.</hi> The <hi>Hebrew</hi> word is directly oppoſite to that uſed in the fifth Commandment. The word there uſed for Honour, ſignifies weightily, and in extraordinary mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to honour. Here in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the word uſed ſignifies to lighten, and to abate weight and meaſure. The fifth Command would be read thus; <hi>Load with Honour thy Father and Mother.</hi> But it is ſaid here, that in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Children had took off that load. They had made great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batements
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:53731:36"/>of the due honour of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. Well, and what then? Why then Hell broke looſe, then <hi>Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,</hi> then <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> then <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs,</hi> then <hi>Sabbath-breaking,</hi> then <hi>Adultery</hi> and <hi>Fornication,</hi> and <hi>what not?</hi> He that allows himſelf in ſin againſt Parents, muſt not pretend to diſallow any ſin: Or if he does, he muſt not be believed to be other then an abſurd Pretender.</p>
               <p>C. 5. <hi>Sins againſt Parents are threatened with the most and worſt of Judgments.</hi> Diſobedient Children are branded for <hi>Fools; Prov.</hi> 15.5. <hi>A Fool deſpiſeth his Fathers inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: but he that regardeth reproof is prudent.</hi> And for <hi>Bruits; Prov.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Whoſo loveth inſtruction, lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth knowledge: but he that hateth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, is brutiſh.</hi> They are told they ſhall come to a <hi>ſhameful end, Prov.</hi> 20.20. <hi>Whoſo curſeth his Father or his Mother, his Lamp ſhall be put out in obſcure darkneſs.</hi> To an <hi>infamous
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53731:37"/>death</hi> and terrible; <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.17. <hi>The Eye that mocketh at his Father, and deſpiſeth to obey his Mother, the Ravens of the Valley ſhall pick it out, and the young Eagles ſhall eat it.</hi> Of old, God commanded the Civil Magiſtrate to put them to death; <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.17. <hi>And he that curſeth his Father, or his Mother, ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be put to death.</hi> Lev. 20.9. <hi>For every one that curſeth his Father or his Mother, ſhall be ſurely put to death: He hath curſed his Father or his Mother; his blood ſhall be upon him.</hi> 'Tis certain therefore, if ye Honour not your Parents, you Fear not him that is able to deſtroy both Soul and Body.</p>
               <p>C. 6. <hi>Sins againſt Parents, very long perſiſted in, are a token of utter Deſertion by God.</hi> 'Tis ſeldom they return that long walk in diſobedience to Parents. O what words do I read, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.25. <hi>They hearkened not unto the voice of their Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:53731:37"/>the Lord would ſlay them.</hi> Child, Child, ſtay and read over this ten times together: If God give thee not Grace to hearken obedient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto thy Father, thou muſt look for nothing from his hands leſs then ſlaughter.</p>
               <p>C. 7. <hi>Childrens ſins are Parents ſorrows, and ſtains in the World.</hi> Prov. 17.25. <hi>A fooliſh Son is bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to her that bare him.</hi> Parents need no proofs of this. <hi>Lev.</hi> 21.9. <hi>If the Daughter of any Priest profane her ſelf, ſhe profaneth her Father, ſhe ſhall be burnt with fire.</hi> She profanes her Father, that is, ſhe expoſes his Perſon, Miniſtry, and Religion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to contempt. Hear me, Children: Under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> true Chriſtians are all and every one of them <hi>Prieſts.</hi> And if you are profane, you ſee what you do. And you may ſee more; <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.6. The ſcandal of riotous Children and unruly, do make a Parent unqualified for the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:53731:38"/>Miniſtry. If you will be <hi>Impious,</hi> your poor Parents muſt be <hi>Infamous</hi> in a meaſure with you.</p>
               <p>The Father of Lights clear your <hi>Minds</hi> from Folly and Ignorance; and cauſe your <hi>Wills</hi> to feel the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive Power of his Bleſſed Word: And to make a moſt free and firm <hi>Choice</hi> of your required <hi>Duty,</hi> which is your undoubted <hi>Intereſt. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> and <hi>Mahometans, Jews</hi> and <hi>Papiſts, Proteſtants</hi> of all perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, agree herein.</p>
               <p>I conclude with this only added unto both PARENTS and CHIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DREN. This word, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the very reaſon of my firſt <hi>Preaching,</hi> and now <hi>Publiſhing</hi> what is preſented. Religion is horribly decayed among us. All ſenſible Chriſtians are ſtill crying, <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Ruine is at our door.</hi> And dream ye not that the beſt <hi>King, Lords and Commons, can keep us ſafe in our ſins.</hi> The <hi>Nation</hi> cannot be
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:53731:38"/>reformed, till the <hi>Church</hi> is. Nor the <hi>whole</hi> of the Church, till the <hi>parts</hi> be ſo. Nor our <hi>Congregational Churches,</hi> till their <hi>Members</hi> be: Which ſaid <hi>Members</hi> then Reform, and not before, when they come to <hi>Davids</hi> reſolution, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.2. <hi>I will walk within my houſe with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect heart.</hi> And <hi>Joſhua's;</hi> Joſ. 24.15. <hi>As for me and my houſe we will ſerve the Lord.</hi> Nor is Reformation to be expected but from <hi>Family-Piety</hi> beginning and promoting it. I mean the Pious diſcharge of Parents du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to Children, and theirs unto Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. For this I Pray and Labour. As in my ſelf moſt certain, that if the Lord come not, and thus <hi>turn the Hearts of the Fathers to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and the Hearts of Children to their Parents, he will ſurely come and ſmite our Land with one or other, or many, or all his ſoreſt Curſes.</hi> Mal. 4.6.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:53731:39"/>
               <p>The God and Father of our Lord Jeſus, grant, of his great Grace, better things. Namely, that in our Lands, <hi>the Fathers to the Children may make known his Truth.</hi> Iſa. 38.19. And <hi>the Children may obey their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in the Lord, in all things; for this is right and well pleaſing to the Lord.</hi> Eph. 6.1. Col. 3.20. Amen, and Amen!</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:53731:39"/>
            <list>
               <head>Books lately Publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Daniel Burgeſs,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt,</hi> at the Bible and Three Crowns in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>A Call to Sinners, ſuch as are under ſentence o Death, and ſuch as are under any proſpect of it from the long-ſuffering, and gracious, but moſt righteous God.</item>
               <item>Three Queſtions reſolved briefly and plainly, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. What Conceptions ought we to have of the bleſſed God? 2. What are thoſe Truths, whereof the Knowledge appeareth moſt indiſpenſably ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary unto our Salvation; and (therefore) to be firſt and moſt learnt by us? 3. What is the change wrought in a Man by Gods H. Word and Spirit, before he can ſafely conclude himſelf paſſed from Death to Life? Being the Summ of three Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</item>
               <item>The Chriſtian Temper: Or, the Quiet ſtate of Mind that Gods Servants labour for. Set forth in a Sermon at the Funeral of Mrs. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula Collins.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A ſeaſonable Queſtion plainly reſolved, <hi>(viz.)</hi> What are we to judge of their ſpiritual eſtate who neglect the Lords Supper.</item>
               <item>And what is that diſcerning of the Lords Body in it, without which men do Eat and Drink their own Damnation.</item>
               <item>The Chriſtians earneſt Expectation and Longing for the Glorious Appearing of the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. Set forth in a Diſcourſe occaſioned by the Deceaſe of that Excellent Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and Miniſter of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>Noah Webb,</hi> late of <hi>Sandhurſt</hi> in the County of <hi>Berks.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:53731:40"/>
               <head>Some Books ſold by <hi>John Lawrance</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>GElls</hi> Remains, being ſundry Pious and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Notes and Obſervations on the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> opening and explaining it; wherein Jeſus Chriſt, as yeſterday, to day, and the ſame for ever, is illuſtrated; by that Learned and Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man, Dr. <hi>R. Gell,</hi> late Rector of St. <hi>Mary Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermary, London.</hi> In Folio.</item>
               <item>The Jeſuits Catechiſm, according to St. <hi>Ignatius Loyola;</hi> wherein the Impiety of their Principles, Perniciouſneſs of their Doctrines, and Iniquity of their Practices are declared. Quarto.</item>
               <item>The Priviledges and Practices of Parliament in <hi>England:</hi> Collected out of the Common Laws of the Land. Commended to the High Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. Quarto.</item>
               <item>A Vindication of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Alexander Oſborn,</hi> from the aſperſions caſt upon him in Mr. <hi>George Walkers</hi> Account of the Siege of <hi>Derry, &amp;c.</hi> Together with an Hiſtorical Narration of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the Nonconformiſts of the North of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Quarto.</item>
               <item>Monſieur <hi>Jurieaus</hi> Judgment, with Relation to the Affairs of <hi>England,</hi> being a Vindication of the preſent Revolution. Quarto.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe of the Nature and Power of the Conventions in the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Quarto.</item>
               <item>Several Diſcourſes; <hi>viz.</hi> I. Of Purity and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. II. Of Repentance. III. Of ſeeking firſt the Kingdom of God; By <hi>Hezekiah Burton.</hi> D. D. Publiſhed by Dean <hi>Tillotſon.</hi> Octavo.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:53731:40"/>
               <item>The Triumphs of Grace: Or, the laſt words and edifying death of the Lady <hi>Margaret de la Muſſe,</hi> a Noble <hi>French</hi> Lady, who dyed <hi>May</hi> 1681. Aged only 16 years. Twelves.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clavis Grammatica:</hi> Or the ready way to the Latin Tongue, containing moſt plain demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the regular Tranſlating of Engliſh into Latin, by <hi>F. B.</hi> School-maſter in <hi>London.</hi> Octavo.</item>
               <item>Orbis Imperantis Tabellae Geographico, Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, Geneologico, Caronologicae, in quibus Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiae Epitome Mappis quo fieri potuit exactiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, deſcriptio Hiſtorica Imperiorum, Regnorum, &amp; Rerum Publicarum, ſeculorum ſeries a Chriſto Nato ad hunc uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> An. 1685. On Copper Plates. Octavo.</item>
               <item>A Relation of the Conqueſt of <hi>Florida</hi> by the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> To which is added, Two Journeys of the preſent Emperor of <hi>China</hi> into <hi>Tartary</hi> in 1682, 1683. Octavo.</item>
               <item>A Help to true Spelling and Reading, with a Scripture Catechiſm. By <hi>William Scoffin.</hi> Octavo.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
